<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Glenn Hoetker</title>
    <link>https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Glenn Hoetker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/my-website/post/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Update to Tools of the trade 1 -- Spelling and grammar checkers</title>
      <link>https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/post/update-to-tools-of-the-trade-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 15:00:15 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/post/update-to-tools-of-the-trade-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I posted Tools of the trade 1—Spelling and grammar checkers, version 3.0 of the Hemingway Editor became available.  The changes are evolutionary, rather than revolutionary, but provide some useful new features. The update is free to owners of version 2, which is generous for an update of this magnitude. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For scholarly writing, the most important changes are the ability to have multiple documents open at once and to import text directly from Markdown-formatted plain text documents, in addition to Word, which it could already do. I found a few issues when round-tripping a draft article from Word to Hemingway and back to Word. Tables were completely mangled and some formatting was lost.  The former is not surprising given Hemingway&amp;rsquo;s more general target audience and would be easy to work around.  Formatting issues seemed, based on quick perusal, to be more common in sections with lots of manual formatting (centering and underlining seemed to vanish, while italics remained).  Styles were retained, although the exported document didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to retain the same definition of those styles. It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to move style definitions between documents, but having to do so does introduce an additional step. Oddly, although it can only import .docx files (not the older .doc format), it exports .doc files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another new feature offers an alternative to round-tripping Word documents.  Hemingway can now export a PDF of your document that includes its informative highlighting.  One could import a Word document, export the highlighted PDF and edit the problems Hemingway found directly in Word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other new features, probably less relevant for scholarly writing, include pubishing to Wordpress and Medium directly from the app and a distraction-free mode that hides unnecessary UI elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you thought Hemingway sounded useful on the basis of my earlier post, you&amp;rsquo;ll find it equally or slightly more so after the update.  It&amp;rsquo;s exciting to see the product continue to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools of the Trade 1</title>
      <link>https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/post/tools-of-the-trade-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 15:08:10 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/post/tools-of-the-trade-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a series of posts on &amp;ldquo;Tools of the trade.&amp;rdquo; It will focus mostly on software, although you can see my thought on using a Mac rather than a Windows computer here XXX. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many, perhaps most, of us choose our tools fairly casually. Inertia may be the primary determinant of what we use. However, scholarship places different demands on our tools, so a more deliberate consideration of options can be worthwhile. The word processor or presentation software you&amp;rsquo;ve used for years may or may not be the best choice for your scholarly work. Also, some useful tools like bibliographic information managers (Zotero, EndNote, etc.) are probably outside of your prior experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first post in the series is about grammar &amp;amp; spelling checkers. Most word processors include at least a spell checker and some, e.g. Microsoft Word, also include a grammar checker. Still, I see two reasons to consider a separate grammar &amp;amp; spelling tool. First, we do much of our writing outside of word processors, including emails and web-based forms. Second, while all the spelling checkers I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered are competent, the grammar checkers are more limited. I&amp;rsquo;ve experimented with two grammar checkers, Hemingway and Grammarly. Both are useful but fulfill different roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hemingway&amp;rsquo;s purpose is to &amp;ldquo;Make your writing bold and clear.&amp;rdquo; It highlights long or convoluted sentences, words and phrases that can be simplified, adverbs and uses of the passive voice. It is up to the author to devise a fix to the problem, although it will suggest simpler alternatives for words and phases, for example, suggesting &amp;ldquo;But&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Yet&amp;rdquo; as replacements for &amp;ldquo;However.&amp;rdquo; Because you can edit with Hemingway, feedback on your changes is immediate, and Hemingway&amp;rsquo;s use of colorful highlighting makes it easy to identify areas of concern. Hemingway is available as a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hemingwayapp.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;web-based service&lt;/a&gt; or as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hemingwayapp.com/desktop.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;desktop app&lt;/a&gt; for either Mac or Windows ($20 at the time of this posting). Either allow you to edit text directly, including basic formatting, although I expect that most people will cut and paste text from other applications. The desktop app works without internet access and allows you to import Word documents and export formatted text as either a Word document, HTML (great for posting to a blog) or Markdown (a plain-text format I&amp;rsquo;ll write about soon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://grammarly.go2cloud.org/SHqp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Grammarly&lt;/a&gt; is a more traditional style checker, looking for errors in spelling, sentence structure, grammar and punctuation. It seems to have a deep style guide, which it applies intelligently. Feedback consists of colored underlining in the text and an explanation of the issue in the sidebar. The sidebar feedback come in three levels. Initially, you see a one-line description of the problem, perhaps with a proposed fix that can be implemented by clicking on it. The one-line description can be expanded for a slightly more extensive description, e.g., &amp;ldquo;Unclear antecedent It may be unclear who or what This refers to. Consider rewriting the sentence to remove this unclear reference.&amp;rdquo; An additional click brings up an extensive explanation, often with multiple examples. Like Hemingway, Grammarly is available as both a &lt;a href=&#34;https://grammarly.go2cloud.org/SHqp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;web-based service&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;a href=&#34;https://grammarly.go2cloud.org/SHqp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;desktop app&lt;/a&gt; for Mac or Windows. Unlike Hemingway, either can import/export Word documents in addition to allowing you to edit text directly. Grammarly also has extensions for Chrome, Safari and Firefox, which unobtrusively check grammar whenever you are inputting text on the web. I&amp;rsquo;ve found this helpful when I&amp;rsquo;m composing announcements on Blackboard, for example. There is also a plugin for MS Word on Windows, which I&amp;rsquo;ve not tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grammarly offers a free tier of services via either the web or the desktop application, both of which need internet access. The free tier includes &amp;ldquo;150 critical grammar and spelling checks.&amp;rdquo; Grammarly Premium offers another 100 checks, suggests alternative wording to diversify your writing, allows you to specify the genre of your writing and checks for plagiarism across &amp;ldquo;8 billion web pages.&amp;rdquo; Grammarly Premium costs about $12 a month via an annual subscription. I&amp;rsquo;ve found it powerful and easy to use. It does have some quirks which I hope later versions will address. For example, it always encourages the use of the Oxford comma (i.e., the second comma in &amp;ldquo;I like apples, pears, and oranges.&amp;rdquo;) Many writers, including me, prefer to omit the second comma unless it&amp;rsquo;s necessary for clarity. While you can turn off broad categories like punctuation checks, I&amp;rsquo;ve not found a way to turn off specific checks like the Oxford comma. I paid for the premium version almost immediately after I started using Grammarly, so I unfortunately can&amp;rsquo;t compare the thoroughness of its checks to the free version, but both share the same easy-to-use interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a demonstration of both products, here are screenshots of an early draft of this post in both (I omitted some text in which Grammarly didn&amp;rsquo;t mark anything).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/Grammarly.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grammarly&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/HemingwayEditor.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henningway&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was impressed that Grammarly caught the error in &amp;ldquo;It will focus mostly of software.&amp;rdquo; I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand why it suggested omitting the comma in the final sentence until I drilled down to the most extensive explanation. So, I learned something in addition to improving this document. Hemingway didn&amp;rsquo;t catch as many errors but was much more rigorous in pointing out hard to read sentences and words that could be replaced with simpler ones. I found the color coding very helpful, particularly regarding adverbs, which aren&amp;rsquo;t inherently bad, but weaken writing when used excessively. Being able to scan the whole document for blue highlighting is a quick way to sense if there might be a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These different results reflect the different aims of the products, rather than one being better than the other, begging the question of which to use. Even though I am an experienced writer and native speaker of English, I found Grammarly an easy to use way to improve my writing. It has saved me from embarrassing typos and lapses in emails and web-postings. It handles drafts of articles equally well. I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason not to use at least the free version and think the Premium version is a good investment if you can afford it. &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:If-you-register&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:If-you-register&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hemingway is also great, but somewhat more limited for scholarly application. It has been very helpful for tightening up the writing in my syllabi, longer emails and similar documents. Unfortunately, even my best efforts at concise, robust scholarly writing turn into massive yellow or red blocks of &amp;ldquo;This sentence is (very) hard to read.&amp;rdquo; An ad hoc sample of articles in my &amp;ldquo;To read&amp;rdquo; folder gave similar results, so I think reflects the peculiarities of scholarly writing. Even so, it consistently revealed multiple opportunities to streamline draft articles. Again, I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason not to use the free web-based version. I think the real value of the paid application, besides supporting the developer, is the ability to import and export Word documents without losing formatting. Since it is only $20, I think it&amp;rsquo;s a reasonable purchase if you consistently find the web-based version helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:If-you-register&#34;&gt;If you register for Grammarly via the links in this article, I get a small referral fee. The direct link, should you prefer it, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grammarly.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://www.grammarly.com&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:If-you-register&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Mindmapping software for class preparation</title>
      <link>https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/post/mindmap-for-class-prep/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 15:55:54 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/post/mindmap-for-class-prep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mindmapping has been around for a long time in various forms and there are many software packages available. In this post, I discuss how I use iThoughtsX to plan my classes. Nothing I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss is specific to iThoughts since many other packages offer similar features. Having tried most of them, I&amp;rsquo;ve found that iThoughts best meets my working style. I especially appreciate its amazing export options and the fact that files move seamlessly from its Mac to iPad versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown below, I&amp;rsquo;ve made a map for my class. Each of the branches shown has many sub-branches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/iThoughtPreview1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
￼&lt;br /&gt;
This makes it a great tool for the doodling around stage of planning, especially since moving an item from one branch to another is so quick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/iThoughtsmovingItems.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
￼&lt;br /&gt;
It also gives me a place to store items I come across between times I teach, so there are all in one place when I come back to prepare for the next edition of the class. I can tag new items with the pencil icon to give me a visual clue that these are new since last time I taught (there are a slew of additional icons available and you can search or filter using them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s all pretty standard application for mind mapping. My real breakthrough came when I realized I could use a mindmap for the more nitty gritty part of planning and organizing the class. My mindmap allows me to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the macro level, layout each class session and how they will fall into larger subject modules.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schedule the readings for each class.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add additional text that will become part of the reading list.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track which classes/modules have been fully prepared and which still need work.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Export an image that I&amp;rsquo;ll use in our first class to illustrate the overall structure of the class&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Export information that allows me to automatically compile all of the relevant PDFs and links, organized into folders by class session.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Export information that allows me to automatically generate the syllabus I&amp;rsquo;ll distribute to the students.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last two items on that list depends on other geeky technology, but even iThoughts itself it can do amazing things. The material that will become the syllabus all resides in the &amp;ldquo;Class Sessions&amp;rdquo; node. First I created a node for each subject module and each class session therein. Because of how easy it is the create/delete branches and move items between branches, I started with a very rough outline and refined it as I went. In the same way, it was trivial to reorganize the subject modules between annual editions of the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/iThoughtspreviewme8_540.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within each class, I created nodes for Readings and Assignments. Having created it once, I copy-pasted it to the other sessions. If appropriate, I added subdivisions for the readings in each class. Then, I created nodes for each reading. For most of them, I copied information over from EndNote, which is how I organize my reference library. I&amp;rsquo;ve set iThought to automatically alphabetize items for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;￼&lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/iThoughtspreviewme4_860.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arrow on the node indicates that there is a link associated with it. That can be a link to a website or to a file (created by dragging the file onto a node). Clicking on the arrow will open the associated file, which makes it easy to re-examine items (&amp;ldquo;How long was the Carlson paper?&amp;rdquo;). I can also add notes for each node, either for myself or, as in this case, to become part of the syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;￼&lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/iThoughtspreviewme5.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;￼&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each node can also be associated with task management information, which I&amp;rsquo;ve repurposed. Here, I&amp;rsquo;ve tagged a class session with the date it occurs, how many days it will take and marked its progress as &amp;ldquo;Rollup&amp;rdquo;, that is, what proportion of the nodes below it have been completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;￼￼&lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/iThoughtsPreviewme7.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows me to see that I&amp;rsquo;ve completed the &amp;ldquo;Setting the stage&amp;rdquo; module (the checkmark) and that I&amp;rsquo;ve dedicated 3 class sessions to it. Because this all updates dynamically, I can trivially track that I&amp;rsquo;ve not dedicated too much time to any one subject and have stayed within the 16 class session I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;￼￼&lt;img src=&#34;https://ghoetker.github.io/my-website/img/iThoughtspreviewme3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
￼&lt;br /&gt;
Once I&amp;rsquo;ve finalized everything, I can take advantage of iThoughts export capabilities, which include exporting to a PDF, a website, images, Word/Excel/Powerpoint (with lots of flexibility), other mindmapping formats, and Markdown. Simply exporting to Word would give one a great start on the Syllabus, needing minimal additional formatting. To leverage the other systems I have in place, I go another route, which I&amp;rsquo;ll &lt;em&gt;briefly&lt;/em&gt; describe just to give a flavor of what is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I export everything in the &amp;ldquo;Class sessions&amp;rdquo; node as a comma-delimited .csv file. I use a short Python script to extract information on each reading, which is used to copy the PDFs for each session into an appropriately named folder. Compiling all the PDFs in this way takes under 10 seconds and guarantees I don&amp;rsquo;t omit a reading. Second, I export as a Markdown file. Markdown, if you&amp;rsquo;ve not encountered it, is a plain text format meant to create a document that is easy for humans to read, not locked into any proprietary format (Word, Pages, etc.), yet able to be translated into PDFs, websites, Word documents, etc. For my purposes here, the key thing is that Markdown is plain text, which means I can take advantage of basic Unix (Python, etc.) tools to tweak it to exactly how I want it&amp;ndash;removing some exported information I don&amp;rsquo;t care about, etc. Then I use the amazing (and free) pandoc software to turn the Markdown into a LaTex file, which I compile into a beautiful PDF. Because I&amp;rsquo;ve written a shell script to do the tweaking and have a LaTeX template set up, I can go from export to completed PDF in about 20 seconds (see&lt;br /&gt;
XXX this posting for the finished product).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is a time-saver (once I used it enough to make up for the development time involved). More importantly, it frees me to refine my class plan without friction. If I want to add a reading, move a reading between sessions, combine two sessions, etc., I simply do so in the mindmap document. In well under a minute, I will have an up-to-date syllabus and folder of organized readings, with no chance for error. It is easy to keep my class up to date and I&amp;rsquo;ve been more willing/able to experiment with alternative organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having set up this system, I use it for all of my classes with minimal change. It&amp;rsquo;s great from the &amp;ldquo;blank-slate&amp;rdquo; stage of planning through producing the final syllabus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t show it here, I use the same mindmap to make detailed plans for each class session. It&amp;rsquo;s especially helpful for my 4 hour evening MBA class, where I have lots of different activities each session and need to be very aware of time management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also used iThought to deliver material in class. For example, I use it to present a timeline of sustainability-related events over the last 140 years. It works great because the map conveys the overall structure, while I can link individual nodes to videos, images, sound clips, websites, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
